Hey בוקר
טוב. boker tov. Alright, today's דף daf is ל"ט. lamed tet. We
are behind, so we pick up at the bottom of ל"ח עמוד
א', lamed chet amud aleph, the very bottom. And we are dealing
with whole issues about slaves and תיקון עולם tikkun olam relating to
slaves, although not necessarily always what we might have thought the thing
on which way the תיקון עולם tikkun olam goes. Okay, and we're
having also a question about whether when you free a slave, when
you renounce property ownership of a slave, does that automatically free him,
or do you need a גט, get, a שטר שחרור, shtar shichrur,
because it's also a personal status issue as well. So a non-Jew,
we're also talking about non-Jewish slaves, which are owned as property. So
now the גמרא Gemara says like this, ההיא אמתא, hahi amata, it
is eight lines from the bottom on ל"ח עמוד א'. lamed chet
amud aleph. ההיא אמתא דהוה בפומבדיתא, hahi amata de'hava be-Pumbedita, there was
a female slave in פומבדיתא, Pumbedita, דהוו קא עבדי בה איסורא, de'hava
kam'avdi ba issura, that people were doing prohibitions with her, meaning that
she was being taken advantage of sexually. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, אי
לאו דאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, ilei de'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel,
if it's not that רב יהודה Rav Yehuda in the name of
שמואל Shmuel said, כל המשחרר עבדו עובר בעשה, kol hamesachrer avdo over
be-asei, anybody who frees his slave transgresses a positive commandment, הוינא כפינא
ליה למריה וכתב לה גיטא דשיחרורא, haveina kafinan le-marei ve-kathav lei gitta
de'shichrura, I would force the master to free her, then she could
free her and she could be married by a Jewish man or
that she'd be treated with more respect because she was a free
woman. Maybe slaves people feel that they can be exploited and taken
advantage of. So that's what I would do, but he felt constrained
to do it because of the teaching of רב יהודה אמר שמואל.
Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel. So רבינא אמר, Ravina amar, now רבינא Ravina
says,
כי הא מודי רב יהודה, ki ha modei Rav Yehuda, רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda would agree that in such a case you are allowed
to free the slave, משום מילתא דאיסורא, mishum milsa de'issura, because the
prohibitions that are being done are
outweigh the positive מצוה mitzvah not to free a slave. Now that's
still sort of saying like it trumps the מצוה, mitzvah, it's not
saying that the מצוה mitzvah doesn't apply in those cases. There are
some ראשונים Rishonim that say differently, as with the famous גמרא Gemara
about well, we'll see, about somebody who freed his slave in order
to make a מנין. minyan. So the גמרא Gemara says, well, whatever
happened to the prohibition that you're not supposed to free a slave?
Okay, so anyway, and the גמרא Gemara says, well, you know, it's
a מצוה mitzvah and so on. So some ראשונים Rishonim again would
treat that as overriding this this commandment, this מצות עשה, mitzvat asei,
and others say that it is not overriding, but maybe the command
doesn't apply when there's a good legitimate reason. Now what is the
מצות עשה? mitzvat asei? The מצות עשה mitzvat asei is based on
the פסוק pasuk of לעולם בהם תעבודו, le'olam bahem ta'avodu, you shall
work you shall enslave them for eternity. Again, very ironic given that
the whole point of, you know, יציאת מצרים Yetziat Mitzrayim is to
speak about the, you know, inhumanity of enslaving other people, other human
beings, and then here we have this מצות עשה mitzvat asei that
you're not allowed to free a slave. And the גמרא's Gemara going,
I don't know, I struggle with it a good deal, we'll see
if it's going to be a little bit debated. It's more understandable
again if you say, what do you call it, that it's only
if it's like being done for no purpose, you know, if it's
being done for a legitimate purpose it's okay. So still doesn't exactly
explain it. I think you have to understand that the idea that
in a society in which the economy is based on that and
you're not dealing with deep systemic changes and you're dealing with individual
cases, maybe it saw this as some I don't know, if somehow
challenging to, you know, the norms, like you know, when the South
said, you know, you're going to completely ruin our economy and that's
why they were resisting it because they couldn't deal with the transition.
But again, you're dealing with a freeing of an individual slave in
a case where the systemic problem has not been addressed. So maybe
somehow that is seen as something that is more problematic. Maybe it's
not even in the best interest of the slave, maybe they imagined,
I don't know.
Perhaps we are kind of backwards projecting our own you know standard
on יציאת מצרים Yetziat Mitzrayim and what things are at play there's
God's dominion over everything.
Yeah, okay, I'm not saying it was the whole point of יציאת
מצרים Yetziat Mitzrayim obviously.
Certainly the הכנה hachanah and so יציאת מצרים Yetziat Mitzrayim but that
doesn't directly address the whole slave labor issue.
Right, I'm not saying that's the whole sort of message of יציאת
מצרים Yetziat Mitzrayim but it still obviously heightens the irony of the
situation about, you know, about. It's one thing that the תורה Torah
tolerates the institution of slavery, right, that you could say, you know,
the תורה Torah obviously the world wasn't ready to change that for
thousands of years from the time the תורה Torah was given, but
it's like it's another thing to sort of deal with what we
dealt with yesterday, which was the only people who own other human
beings are Jews owning non-Jews as slaves, you know, it doesn't work
in any other direction, to say there's a מצוה mitzvah not to
free slaves.
I mean I'm struggling with that also because clearly this section of
the גמרא Gemara has a different perspective on the whole institution of
slavery than we would like. Right, and so I'm just wondering, you
know, sorry.
Anyway, I'm saying tolerating it, you know, is one thing but sort
of reinforcing it seems to be more challenging. Yes?
When we free the slave they become Jewish? Yes. So isn't there
a positive aspect to that, they became a new person?
Yeah, so exactly, which raises that question as well. But again, maybe
the point is, but this isn't a person that necessarily wanted to
be Jewish, necessarily was forced into this position as slaves and they
were forced to do מצוות mitzvot as slaves. So maybe it's also
seen as threatening that way, you know? What does it mean to
bring a person into freedom, make them a free man, a free
woman, make them a Jew,
and you know, maybe they're maybe they're not interested in any of
that and maybe that could be problematic in other ways, but yeah,
how
do you balance the two of them, the negative and the positive?
Which would be...
Yeah, so I don't know, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* basically says, well
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is inclined to say basically says the default
is you don't free slaves. There's a מצות עשה *Mitzvas Aseh* that
you don't free slaves. And here it says, okay well here it
would be allowed because of איסורא *Issura*, because of transgressions that were
being done. Okay, ואביי משום איסורא לא *V'Abaye mishum issura lo*? And
now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues to say, and you mean to
tell me that Abaye would not say that transgressions were a legitimate
reason to free a slave? והאמר רב Rav: חנינא בר פפא אמר
Amar, רבי Rebbi יצחק מעשה באשה אחת *V'ha'amar Rav Chanina bar Papa
amar Rabbi Yitzchak ma'aseh b'ishah achas*. There's a story with a certain
woman, שחציה שפחה וחציה בת חורין *shechatzyah shifchah v'chatzyah bas chorin*. Half
slave, half free. She was owned by two partners, one of them
freed her, one didn't. So she has this in-between status, which is
always the worst to be in the world you know, to be
in like in the middle of two worlds. So she could not
marry a Jewish man, she could not marry a slave, because she
was neither a slave or free person. וכפו את רבו ועשאה בת
חורין *V'kafu es rabbo v'asa'ah bas chorin*. And they forced the master
to free her. Why? ואמר רב Rav נחמן בר יצחק מנהג הפקר
נהגו בה *V'amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak minhag hefker nahagu bah*. Because
people were treating her like ownerless, you know, literally whatever you know,
they they were taking advantage of her. They were treating her like
dirt. They were taking sexual, you know, advantage of her. So, and
she because she couldn't be married to any man, not to a
Jew or to or to a slave. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says הכא השתא *Hacha hashta*? How could you compare those cases? התם
לא לעבד חזיא ולא לבן חורין חזיא *Hasam lo l'eved chazya v'lo
l'ven chorin chazya*. There, she couldn't be married neither to a free
person nor to a slave. So she certainly was going to be
taken sexual advantage of. הכא אפשר דמייחד לה עבדי ומינטרה *Hacha efshar
d'meyachad lah avdi v'minatrah*. Here, she was a slave woman, fully a
slave woman. If there was a problem that people were taking sexual
advantage of her, find her a slave husband and who would protect
her and who would keep off these other men. So here it
is not as urgent to and it's not the only course of
action, and therefore that's why there was a question whether she could
actually whether it was sufficient justification for her to be freed. Okay,
now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* gets back to this idea. גופא gufa.
*Gufa*. Let's go back to that statement. אמר Amar, רב Rav יהודה
אמר שמואל Shmuel כל המשחרר עבדו עובר בעשה *Amar Rav Yehuda amar
Shmuel kol hamshachrer avdo over b'aseh*. Anybody who frees his slave transgresses
a positive command, שנאמר לעולם בהם תעבודו *shene'emar l'olam bahem ta'avodu*. You
shall enslave them forever. מיתיבי *Meisivei*. They ask on this. מעשה ברבי
אליעזר שנכנס לבית הכנסת *Ma'aseh b'Rabbi Eliezer shenichnas l'veit ha'knesses*. Here's the
story that's coming up, famous story of Rabbi Eliezer who went into
the synagogue, ולא מצא עשרה *v'lo matza asarah*.
He did not find ten people who were there to make a
מנין minyan, *Minyan*. ושחרר עבדו *U'shichrar avdo*. And he freed his slave,
and freeing a non-Jewish slave, right, as a non-Jewish slave they're partly
obligated in מצות *Mitzvos*. You free them, they become a full a
full, you know, full Jewish status. ושחרר עבדו *U'shichrar avdo*.
Where am I? והשלימו לעשרה *V'hishlimo l'asarah*. And turned him into a
מצוה mitzvah. *Mitzvah* into a מנין *Minyan* made the מנין *Minyan*. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says מצוה שאני mitzvah shani, *Mitzvah shani*. Ah,
for a מצוה *Mitzvah* it's different. And again the question is what
does this mean? Like if there's an actual מצוה דאורייתא *Mitzvah d'Oraisa*
of not freeing your slaves, how does and only a מצוה דרבנן
*Mitzvah d'Rabanan* of making a מנין *Minyan*, how does that overwrite? So
some ראשונים *Rishonim* still say, like the רמב"ן *Ramban* has a great
line and he says, well even though it's only a מצוה דרבנן
*Mitzvah d'Rabanan*, it is of such great theological weight because the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says כיון שבא הקדוש ברוך הוא לבית הכנסת ולא מצא
עשרה צבור מתפללים מיד כועס *Kivan sheba haKadosh Baruch Hu l'veit ha'knesses
v'lo matza asarah tzibur mispallelim miyad ko'es*. God shows up to shul
and there isn't a מנין *Minyan*, God automatically gets angry. So it's
not just a question of technically is it a you know is
a מנין *Minyan* technically a מצוה דאורייתא *Mitzvah d'Oraisa* or מצוה דרבנן
*Mitzvah d'Rabanan*. It's like profound theological weight and yes that can overwrite
this מצות עשה *Mitzvas Aseh*. But the other answer that ראשונים *Rishonim*
give that they're more satisfied with is that this מצוה *Mitzvah* of
not to free the slaves only means like if it's for no
good purpose. But if there's a legitimate purpose, then you're not it's
not you're not overwriting, you're not even transgressing. Okay.
But he doesn't have to like, you know, do מילה *Milah* or
whatever it is?
No, he already did.
He already did. He doesn't do that and get another טבילה *Tevilah*?
He just like frees him just like that, he doesn't do anything?
Yeah, because you טובל tovel, *Tovel* him when he is a slave,
and you do a מילה *Milah* when you make him into a
slave. So the idea is that this all the acts of גירות
*Geirus* were done to him, but he they are prevented from manifesting
themselves because of the reality that he's enslaved. And as soon as
you remove that reality, that earlier act basically like, you know, comes
to fruit manifests itself fully, is given the ability to fully to
fully express itself.
No. Okay. So when you made him partially obligated in מצות *Mitzvos*...
No, you force it on him, you force the status on him.
So it's interesting, if you free a slave he's going to do
many מצות *Mitzvos* every day.
Yeah, but that's right. So I mean,
yeah, I mean again that's like an interesting question, like it's a
difference between somebody who's like not obligated to so to say they
could become obligated and could do מצות *Mitzvos* is a little different
than saying I right now am obligated and not able to do
the מצוה *Mitzvah* that I have to do, right? So it's again
I I see where you're coming from but it seems that what?
It's not like this is a required מצוה *Mitzvah*, מנין *Minyan*.
Yeah, that's true also. Right. I understand the issue. The גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* doesn't have as much sympathy if you're not in that category
to change your status so that you'll be in a category so
that you'll be able to do more מצוה *Mitzvah*. Like that's seen
as like of a different nature. Okay.
תנו רבנן *Tanu Rabanan*. You shall enslave them forever. רשות דברי רבי
ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael So Rabbi Yishmael is a man after my own
heart. So he basically says that it's not a מצוה. You're allowed
to, the Torah will tolerate the institution of slavery. You don't have
an obligation to keep your slaves. רבי עקיבא אומר חובה, Rabbi Akiva
omer chova, no you're obligated to like we said before. So the
גמרא Gemara. says, דילמא רב אלעזר סבר לה כמאן דאמר רשות? dilma
Rav Elazar savar l'aman d'amar reshus? Maybe רב אלעזר, Rav Elazar, who
was the one who freed his slave, we gave him a whole
hard time and we had to say he was justified to do
it because of ייסורא. issura. So maybe he did it because he
held like, that's רב אלעזר, Rav Elazar, right? Yeah, yeah.
רב אליעזר. Rav Eliezer. Oh, he was the one
with the מנין, excuse me. Excuse me. We maybe רב אלעזר Rav
Elazar did it not because מצוה שאני, but he maybe just held
like רבי Rebbe ישמעאל that there really isn't an obligation. So the
גמרא Gemara says, לא סלקא דעתך, lo salka datch, that doesn't make
sense, דתניא בהדיא, detanya behidya, explicitly in a ברייתא braisa רב אלעזר
אומר חובה. Rav Elazar omer chova. Rav Elazar himself says it's an
obligation to not free a slave, to keep a slave as a
slave. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara said, אמר רבא בהני תלת מילי
נחתי בעלי בתים מנכסיהון. Amar Rava behani telat mili nacheti ba'alei batim
minichseihon. In the following three ways, the homeowners, which basically means wealthy
people, go like, you know,
lose their wealth, go down from their property. Okay, so this is
ways that wealthy people lose their wealth, basically because of three things.
בשבתא, beshabta, I'm sorry,
דמפקי עבדיהו לחרותא. demafki avdaihu lecherusa. They free their slaves. Okay, they
think they're going to be so magnanimous and they have all these
slaves, so sometimes they're nice and they free them.
Well also you have to give them a lot of presents when
you free them.
You give them הענקה, ha'anaka, don't you have to give? Never, that's
עברי. Ivri. Okay. ודסיירי נכסיהון בשבתא. Vedisayrei nichseihon beshabta. Now you could
say, okay, they're just saying it's a bad economic decision, you know,
but it's clear that there's more of a מידה כנגד מידה, mida
kineged mida, a moral or religious punishment because of a sense of
a religious violation. Because the next one is דסיירי נכסיהון בשבתא. desayrei
nichseihon beshabta. They survey their property on שבת. Shabbos. You know, they
go out to their fields and they check that everything's being taken
care of and so on. So there's no practical reason why that
should make them, you know, not be as successful financially. Clearly there's
a type of a מידה כנגד מידה. mida kineged mida. They think
that they're being like so generous, but they're actually misusing
their property as it were.
So in the case by slaves, and by the case of שבת
Shabbos obviously, and therefore they're punished by losing their property.
And the final one is דקבעי סעודתה בשבתא בעידנא דבי מדרשא. dekeva'ei
seudasa beshabta be'idna debei midrasha. So they may be making a nice
big meal, so that seems like a good use of it. And
they do it on שבת, Shabbos, עונג שבת, oneg Shabbos, so they
have a big, big meal on שבת. Shabbos. The only problem is
that they do it when it's time for the שיעור, shiur, when
everybody's supposed to be going to everybody's supposed to go into the
בית מדרש beis medrash hear the rabbi's שיעור, shiur, and you're throwing
a great big lavish קידוש. kiddush. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this, a ruling against קידוש? kiddush?
Exactly. Okay, so it did not mention anything about the drinking. ואמרי,
vedamrei, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, בעידנא, be'idna, ואמר רבי
חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן שתי משפחות היו בירושלים, vedamar Rabbi
Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan shtei mishpachos hayu biYerushalayim,
there were two like important families in Jerusalem, אחת קבעה סעודתה בשבתא,
achas kava'a seudasa beshabta, one established like a big feast on שבת,
Shabbos, ואחת קבעה סעודתה בערב שבתא, ve'achas kava'a seudasa be'erev shabta,
and one a big feast on ערב שבת. Erev Shabbos. I'll go
back in a minute and tell you what that means in a
minute, or I'll tell you two opinions that רש"י Rashi has. ושתיהן
נעקרו, Veshteihen ne'ekru, and they were both uprooted, they were both I
don't know, destroyed or certainly lowered from their status, you know, lowered
from their wealth because of this misuse of, it seems to be
all so good, like freeing slaves seems good, but ultimately it was
wrong and therefore they were punished. Now, on שבת Shabbos we understand
because we just said. What's the problem on ערב שבת? Erev Shabbos?
So רש"י Rashi has two explanations. One explanation רש"י Rashi says which
is I don't know, I find it strange, is that it means
just Friday night. They had a big meal on Friday night. So
what's the matter, big meal on Friday night? רש"י Rashi says, well,
because you're supposed to have more lavish,
more כבוד kavod on your meal on שבת Shabbos day than on
Friday night. That's just a midrashic idea, I don't want to I
you know, take a look, it just says, דקיימא לן כבוד יום
קודם לכבוד לילה. dekayma lan kavod yom kodem le'kavod laila. Okay, so
they, if you look at רש"י Rashi they, and they but they
had such good
intent, היו מתכוונים בשביל דבי מדרשא, hayu miskavnim bishvil debei midrasha, they
were told don't make a lavish meal שבת Shabbos day because that's
when the שיעור shiur is going on. So they said okay, we'll
make it Friday night. But no, then you did something wrong there
too because you're supposed to show more, make more of your nice
meal on שבת Shabbos day than on Friday night. So it's sort
of like a real like damned if you do, damned if you
don't. The other explanation רש"י Rashi has is that they did it
on Friday afternoon. And then it's much more understandable. Friday afternoon, everybody
is getting themselves stuffed and they're supposed to they're not coming into
שבת, Shabbos, you know, hungry for שבת, Shabbos, hungry for you know
with the appetite.
You can't start a סעודה seuda then, you're
not allowed to do that. Yeah, but not like קובע סעודה. kovei'a
seuda. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this,
okay, אמר רבא אמר רב המקדיש עבדו יצא לחירות. Amar Rava amar
Rav hamakdish avdo yatza l'cheirus. Now we're moving on from freeing your
slave, or I mean obviously circle back, but not but anyway, I
mean but like the whether it's permissible to free your slave, but
we're going to go to ways in which a slave might become
you would actually free the slave, you know, the action of freeing
the slave, not the permissibility of such. So he says like this,
המקדיש עבדו יצא לחירות, hamakdish avdo yatza l'cheirus, if somebody sanctifies their
slave, he goes out to freedom. Then he goes free. How does
that happen? And he doesn't either. מאי טעמא Mai ta'ama what's the
reason? So now this next passage is a whole debate רש״י Rashi
תוספות Tosafot tell us how to read it. I'll just tell you
I'm going to read it like רש״י. Rashi.
It's going to be a difficulty in reading some of the words,
but we're just going to deal with that. מאי טעמא Mai ta'ama
what's the reason?
גופיה לא קדיש, Gufeih lo kadesh, you can't actually make his body
holy. Now why can't you make his body holy? So רש״י Rashi
says, well it means if you think of it like I can't
make him into a קרבן, korban, I can't make him into a
beam that I'm going to build into the בדק הבית, Bedek Habayit,
into the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Now the funny thing is, why
can't I just make him some property that's owned by the בית
המקדש? Beis Hamikdash? You know, and the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash can
use him to do their work or they can sell him to
somebody else, which we'll see is clearly an option. So we'll see
about that and תוספות Tosafot says what גופיה לא קדיש gufeih lo
kadesh means is that even if you were to think about that
comparison, I could sanctify my car, and the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
could own it and sell it, but the גמרא Gemara says yes,
but תוספות Tosafot says yes but here's the difference. The car, if
I sanctify it, if you misuse my car, you transgress מעילה. me'ilah.
The car is considered to be like a thing now that because
it's owned by הקדש hekdesh that is intrinsically holy and it's אסור
בהנאה. assur behana'ah. And there's a sense that you can't do that
to a slave. A slave is still, he's both a human being
and property. He can't become a total object so that now he
becomes, how could I be אסור בהנאה, assur behana'ah, right? How could
a human being, you know, be forbidden in benefit? Like nobody can
talk to him because you get benefit from him? He can't do
anything because he's getting benefit from himself? I mean like he's too,
so there's something about that, that like you know he could be
owned but he still remains human being to be אסור בהנאה assur
behana'ah because of a הקדש hekdesh status. That תוספות Tosafot says is
impossible. So that's what תוספות Tosafot reads is that you aren't sanctified
גופיה. gufeih. But רש״י Rashi basically says you can't use him as
an object that's used by הקדש, hekdesh,
you know, directly. גופיה לא קדיש, Gufeih lo kadesh, לדמי לא קאמר,
lidmei lo ka'amar,
you didn't say let I'll just be obligated to pay his money
to the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
So what does it mean if you're sanctifying him, if he himself
can't be holy and you're not just accepting to pay his money,
what does it mean? דהוה עם קדוש קאמר, Dehava am kadosh ka'amar,
what you mean when you say I'm sanctifying him is it means
I want him to be like one of the holy people. I
want him to be a Jew. So we translate your words to
mean that you're freeing him. Now it's a little bit bizarre and
what רש״י Rashi says, he's going to say it later but I'm
going to say it now to help you understand it. Because the
question still is there's a much more obvious thing that you did
to him is that you said let him be owned by the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash so that they can sell him and they'll
be entitled to his proceeds. It's not an obligation I'm accepting on
me, I'm transferring his ownership to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash so
that they can own him and sell his proceeds. Now again תוספות
Tosafot says that's not possible because then he would have to be
אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah and that's not possible. But רש״י Rashi says
no, here's what רש״י Rashi is going to say later on. Even
if you try to do that, you said I am מקדיש makdish
this slave for his value so that the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
could sell him and take his value. I am מקדישים makdishim לדמי.
lidmei. רש״י Rashi would say you know what would happen? He would
get an automatic upgrade and go free. Because why? He says it's
similar to let's say I go ahead and I take my animal
that's a קרבן, korban, this is רש״י's Rashi gives this example. My
unblemished sheep and I say I מקדיש makdish this sheep to be
sold by the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. But so the point is
what do you mean once you said you're מקדיש makdish it and
it has the potential of being a קרבן, korban, you try to
limit its קדושה kedushah but the קדושה kedushah is fully going to
manifest itself in the maximum way. Okay it max it automatically upgrades.
So רש״י Rashi says the same is true here. If you say
to the slave I'm selling him to be owned by the בית
המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, you know, to be sold, that קדושה kedushah manifests
itself in the max way. Now the maximum way is you can't
turn him into a קרבן, korban, you can't turn him into a
beam that's going to be built in the but what you can
do is you turn him into the idea that he fully becomes
part of the holy people. So רש״י Rashi says it's not just
an idea that we're obviously you meant you were freeing him. No,
I don't care what you meant, what's the גמרא Gemara saying is
if you're מקדישים makdishim then the only full status of קדושה kedushah
that can apply to a slave fully is being part of the
holy people. And therefore that's the effect that being מקדישים makdishim has.
Yes.
So usually there's some relationship between הקדש hekdesh and the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash and here there seems not to be the case. And
you know what I would have thought is let's say I מקדיש
makdish you. Yeah. Well I would have said, and maybe
you saw, I couldn't do
that but to me that's to give your value like דמי ערך
קאמר. damei erech ka'amar.
No that's if you say ערך. erech.
Okay but but you meant something.
Well we're going to get to that. That'll be a רבי מאיר
Rebbe Meir who's going to translate to that way but that's not
this approach. This approach is and the way רש״י Rashi understands it
is you were מקדישים makdishim but it can't mean since it there's
a way in which that can express itself fully. The way it
can be fully קדוש kadosh is if he's part of the holy
people and therefore that's what happens. Okay that's the way רש״י Rashi
explains it. Let's take a look continuing in the גמרא. Gemara
רב יוסף אמר רב, Rav Yosef amar Rav, now רב יוסף Rav
Yosef says in the name of רב: Rav המפקיר עבדו יצא לחירות.
hamafkir avdo yatza l'cheirut. If you free him he goes free because
then he's not owned by anybody. Now of course that's somewhat obvious
but the question is going to be well does he need a
גט get to change his personal status? He's no longer owned as
property but what about his personal status? So the גמרא Gemara says
like this:
מאן דאמר man de'amar well the
גמרא Gemara then: מאן דאמר man de'amar מקדיש makdish כל שכן kol
shekein מפקיר mafkir if you say this מקדיש makdish idea which was
a strange idea that you're trying to sanctify him and it turn
translate into him becoming a free person. Then certainly you would say
it if you explicitly free him. אבל מאן דאמר מפקיר, aval man
d'amar mafkir, the one who gives the example of renouncing ownership, אבל
מקדיש לא, aval makdish lo, but if you sanctify him, that we
wouldn't translate it that you're freeing him. דילמא דמי קאמר, dilma d'mei
ka'amar, maybe you mean like we would normally assume, he's owned by
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash to sell for his proceeds. Okay, איבעיא
להו, ibaya lehu, now they raise the following question: צריך גט שחרור
או לא? tzarich get shichrur o lo? When you verbally free him
either by being מפקיר mafkir him or by being מקדיש makdish him,
that's enough to renounce your ownership. You can verbally renounce your ownership
of something, but is it enough to change his personal status? Right,
so now you can't enslave him, but he's not fully obligated in
מצוות mitzvos yet, he's not allowed to marry a Jewish woman, right?
Or that's the question: does his personal status require a separate שטר
שחרור shtar shichrur or does it automatically follow from the fact that
he's no longer owned? You remember yesterday we talked the position of
שמואל Shmuel. that said עבד איש, eved ish, only as long as
he's enslaved does he remain an עבד. eved. As soon as he
stops being enslaved, his personal status changes. But the גמרא Gemara is
now questioning whether everybody says it or not. So let's take a
look. צריך גט שחרור או לא? tzarich get shichrur o lo? תא
שמע דאמר רב חייא בר אבין אמר רב: ta shma d'amar Rav
Chiyya bar Avin amar Rav: אחד זה ואחד זה יצא לחירות וצריך
גט שחרור. echad zeh v'echad zeh yatza l'cheirus v'tzarich get shichrur.
We don't agree with שמואל. Shmuel. You go free in the sense
you're no longer enslaved, you're no longer owned as property, but your
personal status does not yet change until you get a writ of
manumission. Okay, אמר רבא. amar Rava. Now רבא Rava says, calling back
to the idea that מקדיש makdish means that you free him, ומותבינן
אשמעתין. u'mosvinan a'shma'atin.
We ask on our own position.
Okay, meaning רבא Rava quoted this teaching of רב Rav that מקדיש
makdish means he goes free, and then he says but we challenged
ourselves in the following way. ומותבינן אשמעתין: u'mosvinan a'shma'atin: המקדיש נכסיו והיו
בהם עבדים. ha'makdish nechasav v'hayu bahem avadim. So we teach this משנה,
Mishnah, I think ברייתא, Baraisa, excuse me, ברייתא. Baraisa. If somebody sanctifies
his property, המקדיש כל נכסיי, ha'makdish kol nechasai, all my property, and
amongst my property were slaves, אין הגזברין רשאין להוציאן לחירות. ein ha'gizbarin
rasha'in l'hotzi'an l'cheirus. The גזברין, gizbarin, the treasurers of הקדש hekdesh cannot
free the slaves. Okay, because that would seem like they are, you
know, mistreating my property, like I gave this as a donation to
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and you're freeing them? Like you know,
they're misusing the donation. So therefore they can't free them. אבל, aval,
what they can do is, מוכרין אותם לכם ואתם מוציאין אותם לחירות.
mochrin osam lachem v'atem motzi'in osam l'cheirus. Sell them, use the proceeds
for the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Somebody else wants to free them,
let the other person free them. Or maybe they can even sell
them to a person on the condition that the person free them,
although why would the person then buy them? Anyway, but that they
can do. Okay, so basically the idea is they become holy and
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash sells them and uses the proceeds. Okay.
רבי אומר. Rebbi omer. רבי says, אומר אני אף הוא נותן דמי
עצמו ויוצא. omer ani af hu nosen d'mei atzmo v'yotze. No, no,
no, he can actually free himself, the slave. If he has his
own money, can purchase himself for himself, can buy himself from the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and then he'll become free and then he'll
be a free person. מפני שהוא כמוכרו לו. mipnei she'hu k'mochro lo.
That still counts, they can't just סתם stam free him, but included
in the treasurer's right to sell him to other people, one of
the people they could sell him to is to himself. Okay, so
that's the debate of can the slave be sold to himself or
does that seem like they're misusing the property and they're just freeing
the slave and they're not actually, you know, trying to get the
proceeds from it. Anyway, for us, that debate is not interesting, I
mean it's interesting but it's not relevant. For us, what's relevant is
the point that when you sanctify your property and there's slaves, what
it means in the case of slaves is not that they become
free, but that they become owned by the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
to be sold for their proceeds. Okay, so that's exactly against this
whole position of רב Rav that they become free. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this, okay, מותבינן אשמעתין? u'mosvinan a'shma'atin? So the first
answer is what, you want to challenge רב Rav with a ברייתא?
Baraisa? רב תנא ופליג. Rav tanna u'palig. רב Rav. was from the
transitional generation between the תנאים Tanna'im and the אמוראים Amora'im and he's
allowed to disagree. He's included and considered a תנא Tanna as well.
He's allowed to disagree with that ברייתא. Baraisa. Right, well true. תא
שמע. Ta shma. Okay, we're still not done. Okay, אך כל חרם
אשר יחרים איש מן האדם, ach kol cherem asher yacharim ish min
ha'adam, etc. any חרם, cherem, anything under the ban of people, etc.,
לא יפדה מות יומת. lo yipadeh mos yumas. I mean actually the
פסוק pasuk says put to death, but somehow we're going to bracket
that end of the פסוק pasuk and we're introducing an idea that's
so complicated, but anyway that חרם, cherem, using the word חרם cherem
is a form of sanctifying something to the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash.
That's the only thing that's interesting for us right now. And therefore
the פסוק pasuk includes people can be sanctified with חרם. cherem. What
does that mean? So the גמרא Gemara says מן האדם אלו עבדיו
ושפחותיו הכנענים, min ha'adam elu avadav u'shifchosav ha'kena'anim, including your male and
female non-Jewish slaves. So the גמרא Gemara says, so you see you
can sanctify them to the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, okay, and why
don't they become free? Now notice by the way here, you didn't
even use the word קדוש, kadosh, which is, it's not just because
you said according to רש"י, Rashi, המקדיש ha'makdish that it means אני
קדוש. ani kadosh. That's why רש"י Rashi says even if you used
the word חרם cherem it wouldn't matter. If you try to sanctify
them, and you're sanctifying this human being, then it expresses itself in
what a full sanctity could mean by a human being which is
part of, you know, he gets that automatic upgrade, part of עם
קדוש. am kadosh. So anyway, but this says like, no, based on
a פסוק Pasuk in תהילים Tehillim like they really are sanctified. They're
under חרם. Cherem. So גמרא Gemara says no, הכא במאי עסקינן hacha
b'mai askinan what are you talking about דאמר לדמי. d'amar l'demai. You
explicitly said I'm only doing it for their monetary value. I do
not want it to, I do not want them to be fully
sanctified. He said that meaning if you hadn't said that, then how
do you interpret חרם? Cherem? What? Would you interpret חרם Cherem as
a can't have הנאה hana'ah like the חרם? Cherem? No, I don't,
no, but that this idea that רש״י Rashi said that they automatically
get upgraded. But if you say that I'm only doing it לדמי,
ledmai, then it stays to me to only לדמי. ledmai. So the
גמרא Gemara says אי הכי ey hachi if that's true, אידך נמי
דאמר לדמי, idach nami d'amar ledmai, so why don't didn't you, so
you could have just said that before? You could have said that
when when we had the case about the גזברים, gizbarim, right, why
don't we just say that you said it, that you said לדמי?
ledmai? Why do we have to say that רב Rav disagreed with
that position if רב Rav would agree in a case when you
said לדמי ledmai for their value? So the גמרא Gemara says no.
מה? mah? So the גמרא Gemara says no, אי הכי אין גזברים
רשאים להוציאם לחירות גזברים מאי עבידתייהו? ey hachi ein gizbarim resha'im l'hotzi'am
l'cheirus gizbarim mah avidteihu? What would that have to do with the
גזברים? gizbarim? And it's like huh? What? What do you mean? If
you're sanctifying them for their value, so then the גזברים gizbarim are
selling them. So here רש״י Rashi does a strange thing. And רש״י
Rashi says, because remember רש״י Rashi says even if I told you
before that רש״י Rashi position is that even if you explicitly say
לדמי, ledmai, it gets an automatic upgrade, it becomes free. So how
does saying לדמי ledmai help? You should have stopped me right there.
Okay, so רש״י Rashi says this, he says here when it says
לדמי ledmai it doesn't mean you say I'm sanctifying the slave to
be owned by the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash for his value. What
רש״י Rashi says the word לדמי ledmai here means is you say
forget the slave, I'm just accepting on myself to pay his value
to the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. It's a personal debt. I'm not
sanctifying the slave at all. So yeah, essentially. Okay, so so רש״י
Rashi says you did not actually sanctify the slave when it says
you did this חרם Cherem thing. Because again for רש״י, Rashi, when
you when you when you say actually sanctify in any way, it
gets an automatic upgrade. So the גמרא Gemara says if that's true,
well why didn't you say it before? Being he becomes free. Right.
So the גמרא Gemara says רש״י, Rashi, the גמרא Gemara says okay,
so now you're saying it's only you accepted a personal obligation. Why
didn't you say that before about the case with the treasurers? So
it says no. Because the case of the treasurers clearly you sanctified
the slave himself. Something happened to the slave himself because the treasurers
are selling him. It's not just your personal obligation. Okay, so that's
how רש״י Rashi in that case, אי הכי אין גזברים רשאים להוציאם
לחירות גזברים מאי עבידתייהו? ey hachi ein gizbarim resha'im l'hotzi'am l'cheirus gizbarim
mah avidteihu? What does it have to do with the treasurers? ותו,
visu, אבל מוכרין אותם לאחרים והם מוציאים אותם לחירות, aval mochrin osam
l'acheirim v'achayim motzi'im l'cheirus, you sell to other people, then what are
they doing with other people? You're not, you know, it's all about
your personal obligation. It's not about the slave being owned and traded
and sold by the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. ותו, visu, רבי אומר
אומר אני אף הוא נותן דמי עצמו ויוצא מפני שהוא כמוכר לו,
omer omer ani af hu nothein d'mei atzmo v'yotzei mipnei she'hu k'mocher
lo, he buys himself back. ולדמי vi'ledmai and if it's just your
personal obligation on yourself to pay the value, מה מפני שהוא כמוכר
לו? mah mipnei she'hu k'mocher lo? What's all that doing? Clearly there
it's owned by the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So if it's owned
by the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash in that case by the גזברים,
gizbarim, the only explanation is that's a תנא Tanna that disagrees with
רב. Rav. רב Rav. has to disagree with it. Okay, because רב
Rav. would say it's impossible, the way רש״י Rashi explains, even if
you try to limit his קדושה kedusha to be just for proceeds,
once you're מקדיש makdish him himself, he becomes free. So if a
ברייתא Braitah feels otherwise that a בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash can own
him, it argues on רב. Rav, Okay, and therefore that's why we
had to say it argued on רב. Rav, Okay, תא שמע, ta
shma, come and hear. המקדיש עבדו עושה ואוכל שלא הקדיש אלא דמיו.
ha-makdish avdo oseh v'ochel shelo hikdish ela damav. Okay, if you sanctify
a slave, then he actually, he can go ahead and continue working.
Okay, because because because you only sanctified his value. Now what does
that mean? It means it's sort of like תוספות Tosafot point. Like
it's not like the slave himself is, well not exactly תוספות Tosafot
word, but here here's the thing. If I can, if you might
remember from the past, I can be like מקדיש makdish my hands
or, you know, מעשה ידיי ma'aseh yadai to the בית המקדש. Beis
HaMikdash. Any of my labor goes to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
or my slave's labor goes to the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So
here what it's saying is, but you didn't say you're מקדיש makdish
the labor. You say you're מקדיש makdish the slave. So the labor
that the slave produces is really totally the master's, totally okay. So
the only thing that belongs to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash is
the value of the slave. Okay, now what does it mean by
the value of the slave? What? Yeah, but it means to like,
yeah, so I guess as a point what are you going to
sell him to other people? Why would other people want him if
but I think the point is no, you could sell him to
other people
and yeah, that's a good question. Other people would have rights to
his labor, but somehow the labor itself has not been what's been
sanctified. So as long as he hasn't been sold, like yeah, it's
an interesting question. Like why is it that if הקדש Hekdesh owns
him, so anyway, yeah, I'm getting a little confused. It's a good
point. Okay, anyway but the problem is as we're going to see
that what the גמרא Gemara is going to say is let's take
a look at what the גמרא Gemara says. So he's not יוצא
לחירות, yotzei l'cheirus, right. Exactly. So let's anyway, but it is, yeah
I'm It is a good question exactly what so then. Anyway, גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says תמני רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir היא *Tamni Rabbi Meir
hi*. This is רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* דאמר *d'amar* אין
אדם מוציא דבריו לבטלה *ein adam motzi devarav l'vatala*. A person doesn't
say something for naught. Now what does that mean? So now Michael
here we're going to introduce our idea of ערך *erech*. So basically
if somebody says, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* says that if
somebody says by like an infant that's less than a month old,
ערכו עלי *erko alai*, his value is on me, and the ערך
*erech* is based on certain amounts assigned in the תורה *Torah*, so
the value is zero. So basically you should pay zero. So רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* says no, no, no, you don't say
things for naught or this might be not a question about your
motivation but our הלכתית halachically, *halachic* position. We're going to interpret it
as a statement that has meaning. So rather than saying the ערך
*erech*, which is the fixed value assigned by the תורה *Torah*, we're
going to say what it means is the value, the market value
I accept upon myself. That's what we retranslate the word ערך *erech*
to mean the market value. Okay so here רש"י *Rashi* says that
רש"י *Rashi* says that what it means here when you say, and
maybe this explains Dov your question before about לא הקדיש אלא ella,
דמיו *lo hikdish ela damav*, that this דמיו *damav* means that you
accept upon yourself to pay his, not again like רש"י *Rashi* said
before, it's not that he is sanctified for his value, you've accepted
to pay his value to the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*. Okay so
you sanctify your slave and it says the slave is totally not
קדוש kadosh. *kadosh*, that's why he can work, not קדוש kadosh. *kadosh*
at all. You have to pay his value to the בית המקדש
*Beis HaMikdash*. And he doesn't go free. So why doesn't he go,
so remember those for רש"י *Rashi*, the way רש"י *Rashi* is explaining
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, there's two possible models. One is I'm sanctifying
him but I can't limit the sanctity, boom, he goes free. And
the other is I accept the obligation on myself. This ברייתא braita
*braisa* says you try to sanctify him and it became you obligated
yourself. Okay so why didn't it say he becomes free? גמרא Gemara.
*Gemara* says well it's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir*, and for
רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* we're, רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*'s prepared to interpret
statements to mean you've accepted the obligation, the value to pay on
yourself to pay that value, that's more consistent with the idea that
you were מקדיש makdish *makdish*. So for רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* we're
not going to interpret it that he was sanctified which would turn
make him free, we're going to interpret it as you accepted the
obligation on yourself to pay his value. Okay so again for רב
Rav *Rav*, there's two possible models when you're מקדיש makdish, *makdish* a
slave. Normal case I'm מקדיש makdish. *makdish* him, whatever I try to
do, however I try to limit it, he goes free. The other
possibility is I'm not מקדיש makdish. *makdish* him, I just accept his
value on myself to pay his value to the בית המקדש *Beis
HaMikdash*. רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* says you tried to do A, we're
going to interpret it as B. Okay, אין אדם מוציא דבריו לבטלה
*ein adam motzi devarav l'vatala*. So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
like this, הכי נמי Nami? מסתברא *hachi nami mistavra*, that also makes
sense, דקתני סיפא *d'ka tani seifa*, at the end of the ברייתא
braita *braisa* it says, וכן הוא שהקדיש עצמו *v'chen hu she'hikdish atzmo*,
if he sanctified himself, עוסק ואוכל *osek v'ochel*, he can work, שלא
הקדיש אלא ella, דמיו *she'lo hikdish ela damav*, that he only sanctified
his value, which again here means not he's owned by the בית
המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*, but he's now obligated to pay his value
to the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*. אי אמרת בשלמא רבי מאיר היא
שפיר *ei amart b'shlama Rabbi Meir hi shapir*, for רבי מאיר *Rabbi
Meir* it makes sense. אלא אי אמרת רבנן *ela ei amart Rabbanan*,
but if you say it's the Rabbis who argue on רבי מאיר
*Rabbi Meir*, who don't retranslate people's words, so אי אמרת רבנן בשלמא
עבדו לדמי קאי *ei amart Rabbanan b'shlama avdo l'dami kai*, so you
get that the idea that the slave when you sanctify your slave,
so then you own his value and you can therefore sanctify his
value. אלא איהו לדמי קאי *ela ihu l'dami kai*, but him, he
doesn't basically have his own, his own value, how can he sanctify
himself? What would that mean, right? So if you're the owner and
you sanctify the slave, it could theoretically mean he's now owned by
the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash* for his proceeds. But how could it
mean that way if he sanctifies himself? So clearly we're dealing with
a position that is going to reinterpret the words. So we have
two ways of reinterpreting the words. One is he you accept the
obligation to pay, that's the רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* position. And there's
the רב Rav *Rav*'s position which might not be reinterpret the words,
it's more reinterpret the effect. You try to sanctify him, what's going
to happen is he'll become free. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says like this, לימא כתנאי *leima k'tannai*, let's say that this
issue of what happens when you sanctify your slave is a debate
of תנאים *tannaim*. Okay, המקדיש עבדו *ha'makdish avdo*, you sanctify your slave,
אין מועלין בו *ein moalin bo*, there is no מעילה meilah *me'ilah*,
meaning that if you somehow misuse him, okay, this is going back
again against תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos*' idea that yes he can become אסור
בהנאה *assur b'hana'ah*, and now if he's used for some purpose outside
of הקדש *hekdesh*, it's actually a transgression of misuse of הקדש *hekdesh*.
But אין מועלין בו *ein moalin bo* means no, you do not
transgress that violation and you wouldn't bring a קרבן korban. *korban* for
מעילה meilah *me'ilah*. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר מועלין בשערו *Rabban Shimon
Ben Gamliel omer moalin b'sa'aro*, if you misused his hair, that would
be a problem. So what's that about? Anyway, מאי Mai? לאו בהא
קמיפלגי be'ha kamiflagi. *mai lav b'ha kamiflegi*, let's see if this is
the debate. דמר סבר קדוש kadosh, *demar savar kadosh*, one says that
he is sanctified, against רב Rav, *Rav*, he really is sanctified and
therefore you can be מועל *moel*. ומר סבר לא קדוש *u'mar savar
lo kadosh*, he's not sanctified and therefore you're not מועל *moel*. Of
course then he also should be a free person, but anyway. Okay
but maybe that's the debate. So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says, ותסברא
*v'tisbra*, does that make sense, that's what they're debating? היי מועלין בו
ואין מועלין בו *hai moalin bo v'ein moalin bo*, it shouldn't have
been debating whether you transgress מעילה meilah *me'ilah* which is a technical
question of this transgression or this קרבן korban *korban*. And because only
some cases fall within it, so it shouldn't have made it about
that narrow question about whether it's מעילה meilah or not. האי קדוש
ואינו קדוש מיבעי ליה, hai kadosh v'eino kadosh mibayei lei, it should
have been debating fundamentally, one should have said he's sanctified and the
other side he's not sanctified. Also, what's the story with the hair,
right? If it's fundamentally not sanctified, why does he say there's no
מעילה meilah. with the hair? Why did he say, excuse me, there
is מעילה meilah with the hair? Just say there is מעילה meilah.
with all of him. So anyway, let's see what the גמרא Gemara
says. אלא, rather, דכולי עלמא קדוש. de'chulei alma kadosh. Everybody agrees he
is sanctified. בהא קמיפלגי. This is what they debate. מר סבר עבדא
כמקרקעי דמי. mar savar avda k'mankarkei dami. Yes, he's sanctified, but there's
a הלכה. halacha. You don't transgress the transgression of מעילה meilah. when
it's land. So if I sanctify my land, there's no question it's
sanctified, but if you misused it, you would not bring a קרבן
מעילה. korban meilah. That's just a technical exclusion to the laws of
מעילה. meilah So slaves are linked to land and therefore they're also
excluded from the laws of מעילה meilah. and you don't bring a
קרבן. And that's why you're exempt. He is קדוש. It's all against
רב. Rav Everybody says he's קדוש. The question is מעילה. meilah. So
one says there's no transgression because there's no קרבן because he's like
land, כמקרקעי דמי, k'mankarkei dami, ומר סבר כמטלטלי דמי, u'mar savar k'mitalteli
dami, and the other says, no,
he's like chattel and there is מעילה.
meilah. So someone says, wait a minute, אי הכי אדמיפלגי בשער ליפלגי
בגופו? i hachi admiflagi be'se'ar liflagi be'gufo? Then again, what's the issue
about the hair? Say there's מעילה about if you misuse any of
it. אלא, Gemara says, fine, I'll concede that point too. דכולי עלמא
עבדא כמקרקעי דמי. de'chulei alma avda k'mankarkei dami. Yes, A, he's קדוש,
everybody agrees to that against רב, Rav. B, he's like land, so
there technically won't be מעילה. But here's the issue with the hair.
והכא בשער העומד לגזוז קמיפלגי. ve'hacha be'se'ar ha'omed ligzoz kamiflagi. It's time
for him to get a haircut, okay? So the hair is ready
to be shorn off. So does that, is that, it's connected to
him, but it's not like it's, you know, it's seen somewhat as
external, it's not a fully integrated part of his body and it's
ready to be cut off. So there there's a question, like there's
a whole interesting הלכה halacha that when somebody has to go to
the מקוה mikvah and they need to be טובל, we needed a
separate פסוק pasuk to say that the hair have to go under
the water as well because the hair might be seen some way,
it can be easily, it can be cut off from the body,
right? It's not like, so it's not live, right? The hair's dead,
right? Is that right? Anyway, yes, I mean, okay anyway, so anyway,
sort of like fingernails also something of that question, but fingernails are
a little bit closer to you. Anyway, so maybe that is not
like him and not like קרקע karka and if it's ready to
be cut, is it a חציצה chatzitzah then, it needs to be
cut, is that right? No, no, no, there's a possibility that it
wasn't under the obligation of a part of the body that needed
to be immersed. That I could immerse my whole body and have
the hair floating on top of the water or sticking out of
the water like a big afro and I'm still יוצא. yotzei. We
don't פוסק posek that, we don't, we learn from a פסוק pasuk
that it has to go under. But the point is we needed,
we needed a דרשה drasha to tell me that, okay, to tell
me that it's considered part of the body. So here when it's
time to shave the hair, maybe it's not so much part of
the body that it would actually not be considered like the body
of the slave and therefore not have the הלכה halacha that it's
like קרקע, karka, have the הלכה halacha that it's like מטלטלין metaltelin
and therefore like it's chattel and therefore there would be a transgression
of מעילה. Okay, yeah? Yep. Clear? Okay. So והכא בשער העומד לגזוז
קמיפלגי. ve'hacha be'se'ar ha'omed ligzoz kamiflagi. It's time to get a haircut.
מר סבר כגזוז דמי. mar savar k'gazuz dami. It's like the hair
is already shorn and therefore it's no longer part of the slave,
no longer like קרקע karka and therefore there is מעילה. ומר סבר
לאו כגזוז דמי. u'mar savar lav k'gazuz dami. It's not like it's
already shorn. Okay, good. Now we figured out that ברייתא and the
whole ברייתא doesn't agree with רב, Rav the slave is holy and
now we have this interesting debate of when something is time to
be shorn, to what degree do we see it as if it's
already detached in order to give it some different type of a
category? It no longer really belongs in the קרקע karka category. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. ולימא הני תנאי כי
הני תנאי? v'leima hanei tanna'ei ki hanei tanna'ei? Let's say that debate
of if it's time to be shorn is it like it's shorn
tracks the following debate. דתניא ותנן התם. de'tanya u'tenan hatam. רבי מאיר
אומר יש דברים שהן כקרקע ואינן כקרקע. Rabbi Meir omer yesh devarim
she'hein k'karka v'einan k'karka. There are things that are like קרקע karka
but they are no longer considered to be, הלכתית, to be קרקע.
karka. And this is for the הלכה halacha that you don't make
an oath on land. So like classic oaths like where's the hundred
dollars you owed me, no I only borrowed fifty dollars, so that's
a מודה במקצת, modeh b'miktzat, you conceded half of the debt, you
have to make an oath on the, an oath on the other
half that would not apply if we were dealing with land, okay?
Where's the, you know, so let's now take a look. So it's
a similar type of an area where land is excluded from, you
know, technically excluded. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. ואין חכמים
מודים לו. ve'ein chachamim modim lo. But the חכמים chachamim don't agree
that there are some things that are like land but don't count
as it. כיצד? keitzad? עשרה גפנים טעונות מסרתי לך. asara gefanim te'unot
masarti lach. I say to you, I gave you ten vines laden
with grapes, you know, and that you could either, I don't know,
that I transferred ownership, that you could harvest them or something like
that and then you were going to return them to me. I
don't exactly get how that works because they're on my property exactly
where the vines are, but anyway, I say I gave you ten
vines laden with grapes. והלה אומר אינן אלא חמש. ve'halah omer einan
ella chamesh. No, you only gave me five. So is that a
מודה במקצת? modeh b'miktzat? Do you have to take an oath? רבי
מאיר מחייב. Rabbi Meir mechayev. רבי מאיר says you have to, it's
מודה במקצת, modeh b'miktzat, it's not considered קרקע. karka. וחכמים אומרים אינם
ve'chachamim omrim einam No, וחכמים אומרים, ve-Chachamim omrim, excuse me, המחובר לקרקע
הרי הוא כקרקע, ha-mechubar le-karka harei hu ke-karka, no, even though they're
vines, they're counted like land. Okay, so is רבי מאיר saying they're
not counted like land because they're not dirt? They're growing from the
dirt? Is that what he's saying? That anything growing from the dirt
is not קרקע? karka? So the גמרא Gemara says no, that's everyone
would agree something grown from the dirt is considered connected to the
dirt and connected to קרקע. karka. Here's the debate. ואמר רבי יוסי
בר חנינא ענבים העומדות ליבצר איכא בינייהו. ve-amar Rabbi Yose bar Chanina
anavim ha-omdot livtzor ikka beinaihu. They're not debating the vines. Vines definitely
are considered קרקע karka and there it would not be an oath.
They're debating the grapes. The grapes and the time, notice it's time
for them to have been picked. So therefore, רבי מאיר says the
grapes, when it's time to be picked, they're no longer considered קרקע,
karka, they're ready to come off the ground. Okay, רבי מאיר סבר
כבצורות דמיין, savar ke-vtzurot damyan, it's like they're already harvested. ורבנן ve-Rabbanan
סברי לאו כבצורות דמיין, savri lav ke-vtzurot damyan, it's not like they're
harvested. So again, and it's a similar type of a debate. When
do we consider something to be that's connected to קרקע karka to
be like קרקע karka if its time has come to be disconnected?
So there's their whole very analogous debate, right, about that question. So
the גמרא Gemara says, seems like a good parallel. So the גמרא
says no, אפילו תימא רבי מאיר, afilu teima Rabbi Meir, no, רבי
מאיר could even though he holds there that it's like they're harvested,
he might not say the same with the hair. עד כאן לא
קאמר רבי מאיר התם, ad kan lo ka-amar Rabbi Meir hatam, why
does he say the grapes are no longer considered קרקע, karka, אלא
בענבים ela be-anavim by grapes, דכמה דקיימי מכחש כחישי de-kama de-kaimi machash
kachishi that once it's time to be harvested, the longer you leave
them on the vine, the worse they get. So they really are
no longer, not only is it time, but they no longer have
any, you know, viable, not viable, like any beneficial connection to the
ground. So it really is, they're not seen as, A, you're more
motivated to cut them off, and B, just objectively, there's no positive
about their connection to the ground. So they're no longer considered part
of the ground. אבל הכא aval hacha by hair, כמה דקיימי אשבוחי
משבחי, kama de-kaimi ashvuchi mashvchi, if you leave the hair alone, it'll
grow more, even better, you'll get more when you sell it to
the wigmaker. So therefore, even if you've decided it's time for a
haircut, they're more intrinsically connected to the body and therefore would still
be considered like קרקע. karka. Okay, so that was the end of
that digression about things that have time to be harvested or to
be cut and whether they're like קרקע karka or not. Now, כי
סליק רבי חייא בר יוסף, ki salik Rabbi Chiya bar Yosef, when
רבי חייא בר יוסף Rabbi Chiya bar Yosef went to ארץ ישראל,
Eretz Yisrael, אמר להא שמעתא דרב, amar le-ha shem'ata de-Rav, he said
this teaching of רב Rav, that if you're מקדיש your slave, he
goes free, קמיה דרבי יוחנן kamei de-Rabbi Yochanan in front of רבי
יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. אמר ליה, amar lei, oh I'm sorry, and he
also said, excuse me, not only does he go free, but that
צריך גט שחרור. tzarich get shichrur. Okay, so אמר רבי יוחנן, amar
Rabbi Yochanan, so רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said, where were we? אמר
ליה אמר רב הכי? amar lei amar Rav hachi? I'm sorry, so
it's yes, yes, I know, but it's a teaching of רב Rav
that, oh no, because רבי חייא בר אבין Rabbi Chiya bar Avin
said, what was it, was this רבי חייא בר אבין? Rabbi Chiya
bar Avin? No, that was רבי חייא בר יוסף. Rabbi Chiya bar
Yosef. Anyway, anyway, okay so anyway, רבי יוסף Rabbi Yosef said in
the name of רב, Rav this anyway, this wasn't the thing about
מקדיש, we're moving on from the מקדיש. It was the teaching in
the name of רב Rav that was if you're מפקיר mafkir your
slave, he goes free but he needs a גט שחרור. get shichrur.
That, that's the teaching of רב. Rav We're moving beyond מקדיש. So
he said this to רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. רב Rav says if
you're מפקיר mafkir a slave, he goes free and he needs a
גט שחרור. get shichrur. So אמר ליה, amar lei, so רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan said, אמר רב הכי? amar Rav hachi? Did רב, Rav
could רב Rav say this thing that he still needs a גט
שחרור? get shichrur? So the גמרא says one minute. והוא לא אמר
הכי? ve-hu lo amar hachi? You, don't you say the same thing?
דאמר עולא אמר רבי יוחנן המפקיר עבדו יצא לחירות וצריך גט שחרור.
de-amar Ulla amar Rabbi Yochanan ha-mafkir avdo yatza le-cherut ve-tzarich get shichrur.
Exactly what רב Rav said. You renounce ownership of your slave so
you no longer own him as property but you need to give
him a שטר, shtar, a get, a writ, to change his status.
You said the exact same thing. Why are you challenging that רב
Rav said it? So the גמרא says, הכי קאמר ליה. hachi ka-amar
lei. No, okay, no, no. This is what he meant to say.
אמר רב דכוותי? amar Rav de-kavati? What, רב Rav says like that?
רב Rav says just like me? So it's not "רב Rav said
that?", it's like "Wow, רב said that!". Okay, so that's the difference.
Okay, so great, he got support. איכא דאמרי, ika de-amri, some say,
לא סיימוה קמיה. lo siymuha kamei. No, no, no. The problem was
they interrupted him, he didn't get a chance to finish. He said
רב says if you're מפקיר mafkir your slave, he goes free. And
he was going to say but you still need a גט שחרור.
get shichrur. But before he got the words "but you still need
a גט שחרור" get shichrur out of his mouth he says, "How
can he go free? He still needs a גט שחרור!". get shichrur!
Okay so that was the problem, but
in the end they all agree. Okay, okay. אמר ליה ולא אמר
רב
צריך גט שחרור?
amar lei ve-lo
amar Rav tzarich get shichrur?
Okay one minute, doesn't רב say you need a גט שחרור? get
shichrur? Shouldn't רב have, shouldn't רב require it? רבי יוחנן רמי. Rabbi
Yochanan rami. דאמר עולא אמר רבי יוחנן המפקיר עבדו יצא לחירות וצריך
גט שחרור. de-amar Ulla amar Rabbi Yochanan ha-mafkir avdo yatza le-cherut ve-tzarich
get shichrur. Fine. But at the end of the day everybody agrees.
רב and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that even when you renounce property
ownership of your slave you still need to give him a שטר
שחרור shtar shichrur to change his personal status. And that's against שמואל.
Shmuel שמואל Shmuel, says once the property ownership ends the personal status
automatically follows. Okay, here we're saying no, you need a separate שטר
שחרור shtar shichrur to change his personal status. Now the גמרא says
גופא. Now let's go back and look at this same idea but
explore it within the context of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. אמר עולא
אמר רבי יוחנן המפקיר עבדו יצא לחירות וצריך גט שחרור. amar Ulla
amar Rabbi Yochanan ha-mafkir avdo yatza le-cherut ve-tzarich get shichrur. איתיביה רבי
אבא לעולא. eitivei Rabbi Abba le-Ulla. רבי אבא Rabbi Abba challenged עולא.
Ulla. גר שמת. Ger shemeit. A convert died and he has no
heirs because anybody who is born Jewish will always have an heir.
Any other living Jew is at least in some way his relative.
But if a convert died and he has no children and he
has no heirs, his property becomes ownerless. Okay, so everybody it's a
free-for-all. Okay, everybody grabs his property. ובזבזו ישראל נכסיו, U'vizbezu Yisrael nechasav,
and some and some Jew grabs hold of his property. והיו בהן
עבדים, V'hayu bahen avadim, and there were slaves amongst his property. בין
גדולים בין קטנים, Bein gedolim bein ktanim, whether they're whether they're adults
or children. קנו עצמן בני חורין, Kanu atzman b'nei chorin, then you
the you know, you a Jew don't get to jump into his
property and take possession of his slaves. As soon as he dies,
his slaves at that moment become ownerless, that's like הפקיר עבדו, hefkeir
avdo, right? Nobody owns the slaves right now, and if nobody owns
them, they take possession of themselves and they become free people. Okay?
Got it? Yeah. Okay, yes. Sorry, real quick, is it that a
non-Jew can't inherit or that we assume that if someone converted that
they probably don't have? No, neither. It's that if he's converted then
legally he has no he's a new person and therefore none of
his biological relatives are considered his legal relatives. Even if he has
them, he could still have children. You just may have to work
through in a system like ours where they're still technically relatives. Yes,
but anyway we deal things nowadays with you know with wills or
whatever and so. Even if he did have children, right? Even if
he did have children, correct. They're not legally his children. Okay. So,
okay, so basically he died, his property becomes ownerless, so the slaves
become free. Whether they need a שטר שחרור shtar shichrur or not
is interesting, it does not sound like they that they need a
שטר שחרור. shtar shichrur. Okay, but anyway we'll get to that. Okay,
but certainly property-wise they now own themselves. אבא שאול אומר, Abba Shaul
omer, אבא שאול Abba Shaul says, גדולים קנו עצמן בני חורין קטנים
כל המחזיק בהם זכה בהם. Gedolim kanu atzman b'nei chorin ktanim kol
hamachzik bahem zachah bahem. That works by adults. Adults sort of take
take possession of themselves, but the minor the slaves who are minors,
they are not yet a legal entity you know recognized as adult
as they haven't reached the age of majority, so they're not allowed
they in הלכה halacha can't take possession of property. So the same
way they can't take possession of somebody else's property, they can't take
possession of themselves. So here are these poor kids, they're property waiting
to be seized, and they can't even claim them their own ownership
over themselves. And therefore if you grab the minor slaves, you take
possession of them. Okay, so that's the debate. But now the question,
the reason this is a challenge is you רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
said that even after property slaves are made ownerless, to change their
personal status they need a שטר שחרור, shtar shichrur, they need a
writ of manumission, right? They don't automatically become as a personal status
a full free man. The problem here is is that who's going
to write the writ of manumission? Right? Right? The only person who
could write it is dead. There are no heirs, there's no anybody.
So if they need a writ of manumission, they should be totally
stuck. Maybe the בית דין? Beis Din? So he says like this.
וכי מי כתב גט שחרור לאלו? V'chi mi katav get shichrur l'elu?
I don't get it, how could they go free, who's writing them
their writ of manumission? So the גמרא says, אמר, he said back
to him, דאמר לי מדרבנן דלא גמיר שמעתא. D'amar li miderabbanan d'lo
gamir shma'ata. It seems to me like this תלמיד חכם talmid chacham
here never learned a סוגיא sugya in the גמרא. What type of
stupid question is that? Okay, so it's very nice to say it's
a stupid question, but טעמא מאי? ta'ama mai? So what's the answer?
So now that you're done insulting him, what's the answer? So אמר,
I can't believe you asked such a stupid question, even my בעל
עגלה ba'al agala could... no. טעמא מאי? Ta'ama mai? אמר רב נחמן,
Amar Rav Nachman, קסבר עולא, Kasavar Ulla, he's of the opinion. Exactly,
עולא's Ulla of the opinion דגר כאישתו. D'ger k'ishto. He says if
it's an issue of personal status, and by the way, we're using
the word גט, get, now that's not really because we're borrowing the
word גט get from the case of the woman, as the first
תוספות in this סוגיא sugya pointed out, גט get really just means
שטר, shtar, but nevertheless, anyway, the whole idea, you know, there's whole
obviously we're talking about slaves here, it's talking about, you know, women
the whole idea about the writing a שטר shtar and changing the
personal status. So it says just think about that that that that
paradigm of a man's wife, right? It's all about personal status, she
needs a writ to change her personal status. What happens when he
dies? It automatically changes. Okay, so therefore he says כאישתו. k'ishto. Where
are we? גר כאישה. Ger k'isha. מה אישה משתלחת בלא גט, Mah
ishah mishtalachat belo get, his wife is divorced when he dies or
is free, you know, free to herself without a גט, get, אף
עבדו משתלחים בלא גט. af avdo mishtalachim belo get. Here too they're
free when they don't have a גט. get. Now, of course the
point is, well then, why is that different when there are heirs?
If the master isn't alive, then they should just be free. Their
original master isn't there. והחזקתם אפילו ישראל נמי? V'hichzaktam afilu Yisrael nami?
אמר קרא, Amar kra, right. והתנחלתם אותם לבניכם אחריכם לרשת אחוזה. V'hitchaltem
otam livneichem achareichem l'reshet achuza. No, they are passed on, which basically
means the following. Okay, who when we think about the issue of
personal status, I no longer own you as property, okay, but you
still have your personal status as slave. I don't own you as
property, but your still identity is that of slave. My identity why
do I get to write the writ of manumission? I don't own
you anymore. Because my identity to you is still master. Not a
master that owns you as property, but somehow as a personal relationship.
if you wanted to. Right? Our relationship is still master to slave.
And therefore I still have the status that I can write the
writ and to free and to free you. All right? That's how
it normally works. When somebody dies and they have heirs, the heirs
take monetary possession, and therefore they also with that monetary possession comes
the title of master, and they're also the ones that are in
the position, right, to go ahead and to write it. They inherit
because they now own the slave, they now get that title of
master that comes with it, and they would be the ones to
write the writ. In the case of a גר Ger who dies,
what it's saying is the owner the property ownership went away. You
we would start by saying he still has the status of slave,
but there's nobody who has the status of master. And since nobody
has the status of master, the status of slave goes away as
well as the personal status issue. Okay? So the reason the personal
status remained was because there was somebody to whom that relationship related.
You were somebody's slave, maybe no longer in terms of property ownership,
but somebody's slave. Okay, when the guy dies and there's nobody who
inherits, and then there's also nobody who has the identity of master,
and nobody who can write the גט, Get, because there's nobody who
can write the גט, Get, there's nobody who needs to write the
גט. Get. Okay, so that's basically the answer. I don't know it
was such a stupid question, I mean it's a good it's a
nice answer but it's a little complicated. Yes. Right, there's still some
identity of that relationship. Right. So now the גמרא says now listen
to this brilliant question the גמרא has. It's going to sort of
try to say, let's try to replicate that scenario. אי הכי, I
hachi, says the גמרא, המפקיר עבדו. Hamapkir avdo. ראובן Reuven freed his
slave. Okay, verb not he freed, he renounced ownership of his slave.
He doesn't own him as property anymore, but he still needs to
write him a writ of a writ, right? Because he still has
this master-slave relationship with him, okay? And then what happens? ומת. Umet.
Then ראובן Reuven died. So what should happen now? Based on that
model of the גר, Ger, you should say the slave should go
free. Right? I mean he should be he should not require a
writ of freedom, right? Because he now no longer is anybody's slave,
so his personal status should change as well. So the גמרא says
נמי? So that also should just be like the case of the
גר, Ger, the personal status should change once there's he's not owned
by anybody and nobody is alive who was his who is his
master. So the גמרא says it's but okay, אלמה אמר אמימר, Alama
amar Ameimar, so then why does אמימר Ameimar say המפקיר עבדו ומת
Hamapkir avdo umet אותו עבד אין לו תקנה? oto eved ein lo
takanah? That no, he's stuck. He needs a he needs a writ
to change his personal status and nobody and nobody exists who has
who is a master who can write that writ. So אמימר Ameimar
says he's stuck, it doesn't go away. It means that he is
he works for himself because he owns himself, so he gets to
keep his own earnings and so on as an as an economic
entity, but as a personal status he's not fully obligated in מצוות,
Mitzvot, he can't marry a Jewish woman and so on. So anyway
the גמרא says דאמימר קשיא. De'Ameimar kashya. Fine, דאמימר De'Ameimar doesn't fit
our model. Okay, but this now becomes this fascinating idea thinking about
these two aspects: him as property and owned as property and the
idea those who disagree with שמואל, רב ורבי יוחנן Rav v'Rabbi Yochanan
say even when he's no longer owned as property he has a
personal identity status as slave who the master, the ex-master, but he
still has some role as master, is the one uniquely in the
position to give him a שטר שחרור Shtar Shichrur to change that
identity. And then what happens when that master doesn't own him as
property anymore dies? Does his status of slave automatically go away to
becomes a full freeman or is the guy just stuck? And that's
the issue that we have these two opinions about. Okay, let's see
if we can turn the page before 8:30. Okay. אמר רב יעקב
בר אידי אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, Amar Rav Yaakov bar Idi
amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, הלכה כאבא שאול. halacha k'Abba Shaul. We
rule like אבא שאול Abba Shaul that אבא שאול Abba Shaul says
the minor slaves do not take possession of themselves, only the adult
slaves. Okay, in this case of the גר Ger who dies. רב
זירא אמר לרב יעקב בר אידי. Rav Zeira amar l'Rav Yaakov bar
Idi. So רב זירא Rav Zeira said to רב יעקב בר אידי,
Rav Yaakov bar Idi, בפירוש שמיע לך או מכללא שמיע לך? Beferush
shmiah lach o michlala shmiah lach? When you said heard that the
ruling was like אבא שאול, Abba Shaul, did you hear that ruling
explicitly or were you inferring that from something else that was said?
מאי? So the גמרא says מאי כללא? mai klala? So when the
גמרא says like if why are you asking the question? Presumably because
if somebody only inferred it, you want to question whether it was
a good inference. So how could somebody have inferred that ruling that
we rule like אבא, Abba, what's his name? אבא שאול, Abba Shaul,
thank you. דאמר רבי יהושע בן לוי De'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi
because רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi says: אמרו לפני
רבי. Amru lifnei Rebbe. You know what? We only have one minute,
and I'm not I can't get into it. All right, so we
we'll have to end here to be continued.